Guide to the Papers of Cecilia Razovsky (1886-1968), undated, 1913-1971
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, N.Y.
The Davidsons returned to Austin, Texas in August 1959, where they took courses at the University of Texas and in January 1960, visited Venezuela to attend a medical conference. Razovsky wrote to Israel Jacobson; "We have never been to Venezuela and Morris is especially interested to round out his studies of Latin America... Morris has in mind a book; he has been encouraged to write it by editors of publications to whom he had submitted some of his material." When she returned from Venezuela, Razovsky served on the United Nations Speakers' Services for World Refugee Year and as Secretary for the Austin Committee for Refugees. The couple planned to return to Brazil in March 1960 to conduct research for Dr. Davidson's book, but it appears they postponed their trip and Dr. Davidson's book may never have been published. 57
In October 1961, the Davidsons moved to El Paso, Texas, as Razovsky wrote, "a frontier town with all the zest and exhilaration of a border city with its exoticism and unexpectedness..." Dr. Davidson opened a free clinic downtown and Razovsky volunteered, first as caseworker and later as Associate Director, for the Social Service Department of the Jewish Community Council where she convinced its Board to hire a social worker. She also helped create and served as Chairman for the El Paso Committee for Cuban Refugees, in anticipation that there would be an influx of refugees coming into El Paso; however, the immigration officials directed the migration into Brownsville and Houston and her committee became inactive. 58
At the request of an old friend, Read Lewis, Executive Director of the American Council for Nationalities Service (ACNS), Razovsky completed a detailed report on Mexican immigration into El Paso. Between 1933 and 1934, Razovsky had worked for the Common Council for American Unity, a predecessor agency to ACNS, as editor of the Common Council's bulletin Interpreter Releases. Lewis wished to determine if ACNS should open an International Center in El Paso, and in Razovsky's usual manner, she threw herself full fledged into her work. Despite Razovsky's detailed and lengthy report, and her persistent efforts to arrange free building space in the community, the project may not have been launched. 59
In 1963, the Davidsons visited South America for what would be Razovsky's last time, stopping in Mexico City, Mexico; Lima, Perú; Buenos Aires, Argentina; and São Paulo, Rio de Janeiro, and other cities in Brazil. Beginning their trip in Mexico City, Mexico on May 4, 1963, where they stayed for a week, they revisited old contacts, attended special events, and talked with the local people and professional scholars in order to determine social and political changes. Although Mexico's economy was stable, the peasants were very poor, there was much political corruption, and many young people wished to learn English in order to obtain jobs in the United States. Among the individuals they visited was the HIAS representative, still in his post, that Razovsky had investigated for his state of health in 1959. The HIAS representative stated that the Mexican government was "loathe" to take Cuban refugees unless they held transit visas for the United States. They also attended a program held at the Institute of International Law of Mexico honoring Israeli Ambassador to Mexico, Mordecai Schneerson, where they heard a "purported Jewish Mexican Indian (he looked Indian) who sang in poorly pronounced Yiddish." 60
Arriving in Lima, Perú on May 12, 1963, where they stayed for two weeks, the Davidsons found Lima to be more developed despite the country's continuing high inflation. Razovsky learned no new Jewish immigration had occurred recently and anti-Semitism still existed in rumors such as Jewish domination of the economy. The couple had many interesting discussions with old and new contacts concerning the poverty among Indians, the differences between the Indian culture and history in Mexico and Peru, and the government's desire to combat illiteracy. They toured a nunnery involved in welfare work, the National Catholic Welfare Office that handles immigration cases, the National Library, the School of Social Work, and two Indian barrios. Upon seeing Indian women and children clad in rags, and their "wrecked miserable huts," Razovsky writes; "As we stood outside the priests house... and looked at the children many crying for food-we were heartsick and CR prayed for a Jane Addams- to arouse the women of Lima to try to improve conditions on a national scale..." 61
On May 26, 1963, the couple arrived in Buenos Aires, Argentina for another two-week stay, where they experienced the country in the midst of a military takeover and terrible inflation. Razovsky discovered that many of the Hungarians who had arrived in 1957 had either returned to Hungary or had immigrated to other Latin American countries. Middle class workers were leaving for Europe and the United States; the Argentine government had not paid its workers in three to four months. The Davidsons attended a seminar held at by the Sociology Congress, where speakers were "freely worrying" about the military takeover, the lack of Argentinian leadership, and the transition from a Church to a secular society. The Jewish community was deeply troubled over the neo-Nazism and anti-Semitism in some of the running political parties. Razovsky writes, "everyone is fearful and wants to get out. Very little music, dancing, cheerfulness. Everyone somber." Razovsky lectured on international social casework and internal migration for the National School of Social Work. She writes; "BA [Buenos Aires] know very little about post war experiences in Europe since they did not work with UNRRA." She also spoke to a leadership training class on Jewish international casework at the Jewish center, HEBRAICA. 62
From June 9 until November 19, 1963, the Davidsons lived in Brazil. For the first two weeks, the couple stayed with their dear friends Ludwig and Luisa Lorch in São Paulo, whom they had first met in 1937 when Razovsky evaluated conditions for German refugees in Brazil for the NCC. Razovsky first stop was the HIAS office, where she was welcomed by several of her former colleagues. She also met with her good friend Susanna Franks who asked Razovsky to conduct a volunteer training course for the Liga Feminina (Brazil's NCJW). The couple then spent two weeks in Rio de Janeiro, where they met with friends, and where Razovsky visited the CIME office, attended lectures at the Academy of Letters and a seminar at the Catholic School of Social Work, and visited another school of social work and the Indian Embassy. Following, the couple spent nine days touring Bela Horizonte, Ouro Preto, Brasilia, and Salvador da Bahia before returning to Rio de Janeiro on July 23, 1963 for an additional three-week stay. There, Razovsky attended a Congress held by the International Association of Family Welfare with her friends Susanna Frank and Flora Levine. On August 13, 1963, the couple returned to São Paulo for a month's stay. Razovsky visited several welfare agencies, among which was the Confederación Evangelista, which managed immigration port reception and integration. Apparently there was little immigration into Brazil, and the social worker she spoke with was working on a colonization project to settle dispossessed squatters. The Davidsons toured the Albert Einstein Hospital, still in its construction phase, which was "to be a showplace to show Brasilians Jews are grateful for having been given refuge in Brasil." She attended seminars at the School for Social Work, and visited the Conselho de Assistencia Social that she had been in charge of in 1957. The couple spent five weeks in Campos do Jordão, where they heard news of strikes and a threat of martial law occurring in São Paulo. They left Campos do Jordão for São Paulo, relieved that no martial law was instituted, but were welcomed with a taxi strike. Razovsky writes; "As MD [Dr. Morris Davidson] put it Brasil is having a cold civil war-strikes every day-middle class fighting government and labor." On October 30, 1963, they were forced back to their hotel upon seeing 10,000 strikers marching. They returned to El Paso, Texas on November 22, 1963, the day John F. Kennedy was assassinated. She writes, "Shall we ever know the whole truth? Except that the organizations preaching hate are to blame!!" 63
The Davidsons' return to the United States did not signal an end to their traveling. Choosing San Diego, California as a retirement site, the Davidsons moved into a studio apartment close to San Diego State College on November 30, 1963. During this time, Razovsky wrote her manuscript, "Forty Thousand New Brazilians," which tracked the Jewish community's progress in Brazil through Razovsky's visits there that occurred in 1937, 1946-1947, 1954, 1957-1958, and 1963.
She sent the manuscript to several colleagues, asking for editorial comments and suggestions for possible publishing venues, however, it does not seem that she sent the manuscript out to publishers. In June 1964 the Davidsons attended two welfare conferences in Los Angeles; they then visited San Francisco and lived for a month in Berkeley. Razovsky writes, "We are now trying to decide where to go when we leave Berkeley around the 26 th--Dallas? El Paso? San Diego? Wash? Chicago? Montreal? Brazil?" They chose to visit Razovsky's brother Robert in Dallas in September 1964, then flew to El Paso for a week and returned to San Diego on October 22, 1964. They were "too sick and weary" to attend the funeral of Maury, Razovsky's brother, who died on October 25, 1964 in St. Louis, Missouri. The couple moved out of their studio into a more luxurious apartment in San Diego in December 1964. 64
Both Razovsky and Dr. Davidson began to suffer from health problems. In April 1965, Razovsky had surgery, perhaps for ovarian cancer, in Los Angeles. Dr. Davidson suffered from two hemorrhages in one of his eyes. Razovsky writes, "I wish we were in Dallas so family can comfort us..." By January 1966, Dr. Davidson could no longer use his right eye and Razovsky needed to read for him. 65
Razovsky still kept active in immigration affairs. In 1967, she was serving as Chairman of the International Committee for Social Work, which was formed under the San Diego branch of the National Association of Social Work. In what seems to be her last documented project, Razovsky was trying to construct an agency in San Diego to handle problems of Mexican-Americans and aliens. 66
After a lifetime of service in social work and immigration relief, Razovsky succumbed to a long illness, and at the age of 81, she passed away on September 27, 1968. She was survived by her husband, two brothers ( Robert Ross in Dallas, TX and Julius Razovsky in St. Louis, MO ) and her sister Malcka R. Sterns in Tel Aviv, Israel. In a poignant obituary, Ralph Segalman from Austin, TX writes:
Cecilia's death is a loss to all of us, not because of her Jewishness, which was positive; not because of any extraordinary behavioral science knowledge or social work skill, but because of her heart and her concern for people, which unfortunately are all too hard to find among our professional colleagues... She was one of the last of a fast disappearing breed-namely those who are sincere in their concern for others-not just those in their clinic but those who are 'out there' and need to be helped, and even those who don't know that they can be helped..." 67
Chronology
May 4, 1886 Born in St. Louis, MO to Minna (Meyerson) and Jonas Razovsky.
1904-1917 Volunteered as a teacher and a club leader for the Jewish Educational Alliance, St. Louis, MO
1909-1917 Taught evening classes to foreigners in public school for the St. Louis Board of Education
1911-1918 Handled cases of delinquent children as an employment attendance and probation officer for St. Louis Board of Education
April 1918-1920 Enforced the child labor law as an inspector for the Child Labor Division of the US Children's Bureau in Washington, D.C.
1921-1932 Hired as Executive Secretary of the National Council of Jewish Women's (NCJW) Department of Immigrant Aid
1921-1930 Edited NCJW's The Immigrant
1922-1934 Appointed Associate Director of NCJW. Publishes What Every Emigrant Should Know.
1923 Surveyed conditions for Jewish refugees in European ports.
September 1923 Appointed as one of NCJW delegates to the First World Congress of Jewish Women in Austria, and chaired its session on migration
1924 Visited Cuba to study refugee conditions and plan a community center. Her report helped NCJW obtain funding to create a model refugee program in Havana.
1925-1935 Secretary, Jewish Committee for Cuba
1926-1929 Published What Every Woman Should Know About Citizenship. Served in different capacities for the National Conference of Social Work: 1926 Vice chairman of Division X, 1927 Chair of Division X, 1928 Chair of Conference on Immigration Policy.
1926 Reported on Jewish refugees in ports in Juarez, Mexico and Canada.
1927 Weds Dr. Morris Davidson.
1929 Served as an official delegate to the International Association for the Protection of Migrants, an advisory committee to the League of Nations in Geneva, Switzerland.
1930 Reported on Jewish refugees conditions in ports in Tia Juana, Mexico.
1930-1937 NCJW Representative for the Joint Legislation Committee of national organizations interested in immigrant legislation.
1931 Visited Soviet Russia to study social services.
1932 Chairman of committee to study effect of increased fees National Council on Naturalization and Citizenship; author of Handicaps in Naturalization (Congressional Record 1932), published by the National Council on Naturalization and Citizenship) that caused Congress to reduce naturalization fees; Represented NCJW at the World Conference of Jewish Women (Vienna, Austria); Member of Committee on contact with Jewish communal agencies and committee for social work for aliens at the International Conference on Social Work (Frankfurt-am-Main, Germany); appointed by Jane Addams.
1933 Chaired committee of 12 specialists appointed by Secretary of Labor Perkins to advise Committee of Forty-Eight on Ellis Island and other port conditions.
1933-1936 Served as Chair on General Committee of Immigrant Aid at Ellis Island and NY Harbor.
January 1934 Created a document at NCJW citing the need for a coordinating agency (she calls it "American or Emergency Joint Bureau for German Refugees"). This agency becomes the National Coordinating Committee.
1934 Loaned to the National Coordinating Committee by NCJW, served as Executive Director. Also served as Executive Secretary of the German-Jewish Children's Aid.
1937 Accompanied by her husband on trip to various Latin American countries to study immigration possibilities. Reported on port conditions in Brazil and Argentina. Served as Secretary for the General Committee of Immigrant Aid at Ellis Island and NY Harbor.
1938 Making Americans, published by the National Council of Jewish Women.
June 1939 Witnessed the debarking of S.S. St. Louis, a ship holding 930 Jewish Refugees that was denied access to Cuba. Tried to maintain the Refugees' morale and prevent suicide attempts.
1939 National Refugee Service created, Razovsky served as Director of the Migration Department.
1940 Participated in the establishment of a refugee haven in Sosua, Dominican Republic.
August 1940 Promoted to Assistant to Executive Director of NRS
September 1940 Negotiated, with the help of Evelyn Hersey (Executive Director, American Committee for Christian Refugees), the admission of SS Quanza into the United States, after being denied landing rights in Mexico.
June 15, 1943 Resigned from NRS following a change in board leadership.
September 1943-October 1944 Worked as Chief of Special Services and Editor of Interpreter Releases, Common Council for American Unity, NY.
October 1944-July 1945 Appointed as a Displaced Persons Specialist for the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA). Loaned by UNRRA to the Paris headquarters of the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee (AJDC).
July 1945-September 1945 Returned to New York and worked as a Consultant for the UNRRA Public Information Division, addressed various groups on behalf of the UNRRA.
October 1945-February 1946 Arranged a leave without pay. Resigned from UNRRA on February 14, 1946
February 1946-September 1946 Worked as Director of Emigration Operations for Germany and Austria for the ADJC.
October 1946-December 1946 Visited Brazil, Argentina, and other South American countries on behalf of AJDC.
March 1947-1948 Worked as a Consultant for the Citizens Committee on Displaced Persons.
1948 Retired to join husband in Jackson, MS, where Dr. Davidson worked as an ophthalmologist at the Veterans Hospital. Spoke on behalf of AJDC annual campaign in the South. Worked temporarily at the Family Service Association and volunteered for local civic agencies such as Community Chest, Jackson Juvenile Council, Veterans Hospital (American Red Cross), and others.
March-November 1950 Comes out of retirement to work as a field representative for the United Service for New Americans. Visited six southern states to encourage Jewish communities to accept family refugee quotas and to assist with problem cases.
1954 Visited Israel and Brazil.
February-June 1956 Worked as Assistant Editor for the Hadassah Newsletter in New York.
1957-1958 Moved to Austin, TX. Worked as a South American Resettlement Supervisor for the United Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society Service. Visited Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Ecuador, Mexico, Panama, Paraguay, and Peru.
December 1960 Studied Cuban Refugees fleeing Castro in Tampa, FL, for the United States Committee for Refugees.
January 1961 Attended the conference called by the U.S. government to plan a resettlement program for Cuban refugees fleeing Castro that was held in Miami Beach, FL. Among those refugees she found several families whom she assisted in Cuba in 1924.
Fall 1961 Moved to El Paso, Texas, where Dr. Davidson resumed his practice. Volunteered for Social Service Dept. of Jewish Community Council.
1963 Revisited Latin America, at invitation of friends she had worked with in her previous visits: in Mexico City, Lima, Peru, Buenos Aires, Argentina, Rio de Janeiro, Brasilia, São Paulo, and Brazil. Led training courses in social service for volunteers, and addressed faculty members and graduate students at various schools of social work.
1964 Moved to San Diego, CA.
September 27, 1968 Passed away at age 81.
Memberships
American Association of Social Workers
Charter member, Academy of Social Workers
American Council for Nationalities Service
American Immigration and Naturalization Conference
International Conference of Social Work
El Paso County National Association of Social Workers
National Council, U.S. Committee for Refugees
National Council of Jewish Women
Board of National Council on Naturalization and Citizenship
Steering Committee of Overseas Committee of National Council of Jewish Women
National Committee of American Joint Distribution Committee
Chairman, Conference on Immigration Policy (1925-1929?)
Vice President, Capitol B & PW, Jackson, MS
First Vice President, Hadassah, Jackson, MS
President, Hadassah, Austin, TX
Coordinate Women's Organization for Civil Defense, Jackson, MS
Mississippi Conference of Social Work
Footnotes
1. Biographical Sketches and Resumes, Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, P-290, Box 1/Folder 2, Collection of the American Jewish Historical Society, Waltham, MA, and New York, NY.
2. U.S. Department of Labor, Office of the Assistant Secretary of Policy, "Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938: Maximum Struggle for a Minimum Wage," http://www.dol.gov/asp/programs/history/flsa1938.htm".
3. Statement, 1964, Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 1, Folder 2.
4. Biographical Sketches and Resumes, Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 1, Folder 2; "The Operation of the Three Per Cent Law," March 1922, Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 1, Folder 6.
5. Biographical Sketches and Resumes, Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 1, Folder 2.
6. Letter from Israel G. Jacobson to Razovsky, November 8, 1960, Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 2, Folder 3.
7. Breitman, Richard and Alan M. Kraut. American Refugee Policy and European Jewry, 1933-1945. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1987, pgs. 49-51.
8. White, Lyman Cromwell. 300,000 New Americans: The Epic of a Modern Immigrant-Aid Service. New York: Harper & Brothers, 1957, pgs. 33-38, 47.
9. White, pgs. 34-42
10. Refugee Relief Work-Refugees to South America. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 3, Folder 5.
11. Letter from Razovsky to Armand Wyle, December 23, 1938. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 3, Folder 4.
12. Memo by Razovsky, September 1961. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 3, Folder 7.
13. Report, February 16, 1940. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 4, Folder 2.
14. Schoenhals, Kai. "An Extraordinary Migration: Jews in the Dominican Republic." Caribbean Review, Vol. XIV, No. 4, pg. 17, 41; The Brookings Institution. Refugee Settlement in the Dominican Republic: A Survey Conducted Under the Auspices of the Brookings Institution, Washington, D.C., 1942, pg. 281, 286-287, 296.
15. Report by Razovsky, September 16, 1940. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky. Box 5, Folder 1; White, pg. 61.
16. Friedman, Max Paul. Nazis and Good Neighbors: The United States Campaign against the Germans of Latin America in World War II. New York: Cambridge University Press, 2003, pg. 108
17. Statement, by Peter Bohm, April 22, 1943. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky. Box 4, Folder 7.
18. Monthly Report by Razovsky, June 1942. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky. Box 4, Folder 8.
19. Report to Abrahamson by Razovsky, February 4, 1943. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky. Box 4, Folder 8; Friedman, pg. 165.
20. Letters between Razovsky and Executive Committee, May 4 and 12, 1943. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky. Box 5, Folder 2.
21. Nevins, Allan. Herbert H. Lehman and His Era. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1963, pgs. 221-224, 230-234.
22. Letter from Razovsky to A.M. Warren, April 2, 1943, Collection of Cecilia Razovsky. Box 5, Folder 2.
23. Letter from Razovksy to C.H. Kramer, September 8, 1944. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 6, Folder 1; Letter from Hertha Kraus to Razovsky, July 7, 1944, Box 5, Folder 2.
24. Report, "the Jews Surviving in the Buchenwald Concentration Camp," April 21, 1945. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 6, Folder 1.
25. Report from Chaplain Aaron Kahan to Chaplain Major Judah Nadich, April 22, 1945. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 6, Folder 1.
26. Collected Notes on Razovsky Lecture, by Sylvia Milrod, July 25, 1945. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 6, Folder 1.
27. Biographical Sketch, undated; Memo from Razovsky to T.T. Scott, February 23, 1945. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 6, Folder 1.
28. American Jewish Committee. American Jewish Yearbook 5707 (1946-47). Philadelphia, Jewish Publication Society of America, 1946, pgs. 205-207, 218-220, 309.
29. Resume, undated. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 1, Folder 2.
30. American Jewish Committee, AJYB, 1946-1947, pg. 223; 1947-1948, pg. 212; Address by Rabbi Philip S. Bernstein, October 1, 1946. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 6, Folder 3.
31. Memorandum re sailing of steamers, by Razovsky, May 20, 1946. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 6, Folder 2.
32. American Jewish Committee, AYJB, 1947-1948, pg. 277; Cable from Luis Lorch to JDC New York, September 9, 1946. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 6, Folder 4.
33. American Jewish Committee, AYJB, 1945-1946, pg. 480; Letter from Lightman to JDC New York, December 2, 1946. Collection of Cecilia Razovsky, Box 6, Folder 4.